Avanish Anand

Senior Java Developer (Contracting at Apple Inc.)

Summary

Senior Java J2EE Developer with 9 years of experience in Application Analysis, Design, Development, Integration, deployment and Maintenance/Support for Web, Standalone, and Client-Server based Software Applications in sales service and banking domains.

Rich work exposure in software development with responsibilities as Full Stack Developer, Software Analyst, Project Leader, Software Architect, Team Leader, Team Member and Onsite Coordinator.

Excellent background in developing applications using Java, J2EE on JBOSS Application server Some of the technologies extensively worked on during my tenure in Software Development are HTML, CSS, Servlets,

JSP, Angular 1.5.X, Struts, Spring, AJAX, RESTFul services using JAX-RS and Jersey, SOAP services using WS Annotations, Hibernate, Apache, Tomcat, JDBC and Databases like Oracle.

Strong work experience on the Front End UI development with Java servlet and JSP.

Experience in open frameworks like Struts and spring and reusable Business component design and development (EJB)

Proficient in using Eclipse, SQL Developer and SOAPUI

Have excellent written and communication skills in English and as a programmer analyst I use this skill to communicate directly with the client and gather details on requirement.

Proficient in reengineering the process and improving it to make the business effective and efficient. Have also involved and contributed a lot in converting the requirements into effective business design

Highly successful software programmer having knowledge of all the stages of Software Development Life Cycle

Good team player

Excellent analytical skills have helped me in finding the root cause of most complex issues and fixing them on time.

Strongly motivated and goal-oriented.

Very good in multitasking, can juggle 8+ balls in the air and never drop any of them.

Experience

Senior Java Developer

December 2016 - Present

Started as a Java Developer in Identity Management Services in Apple.

Senior Java Developer at Wells Fargo

May 2016 - December 2016 (7 months)

CSO Migration (G2T)

Description: CSO is Wells internal application developed to manage and order cards for their internal employees.

Responsibilities:

- Analyzing the legacy code written in Java over Struts framework and rewriting it using Spring framework.
- Provided the technical design after understanding the current code and taking all the inputs from all stakeholders.
- Working as one of the key developers in development of different modules using Java, J2EE, spring, Oracle, Hibernate, RESTFul services using JAX-RS and Jersey.
- Leading the overall team of 4 developers by explaining them the requirement and helping them with all techno functional queries.
- Good hands on experience as a Java developer while working on this project.
- Developed REST services using JAX-RS and Jersey.
- I was actively involved during requirement gathering phase for this project. During this phase, I was required to understand business requirement from business users, map them to the technology and processes, discuss the functional and technical solution to business users and obtain timely sign off.

Environment: Java, J2EE, JSP, Servlets, JDBC, JavaScript, HTML, AJAX, Spring Framework, Eclipse, Oracle.

Java Developer at Apple

February 2016 - April 2016 (2 months)

DEP(Device Enrollment Program)

Description: Tesla is a device enrollment program developed for enrolling multiple iOS and OS X devices by different organizations. Business and Educational enterprises uses this application on a large scale to have a control on devices distributed among their Students, Employees.

Responsibilities:

Working as a core developer in developing different modules for DEP program using Java, J2EE, spring, Oracle, Shell Scriptng.

Working very closely with client by taking requirements and completing it on time.

Responsible for resolving existing production issues for different organizations by interacting with different business users.

Involved in coding of JSP programs, which access java beans and JavaScript is used for validations.

Applied J2EE patterns such as DTO, Service Locator, MVC. Building the whole application from the ground up

using multi-tiered architecture using all these patterns.

Worked closely with DBA in development of table schemas, procedures, views and triggers.

Good hands on experience with concurrency framework while working on this project.

Coordinated with QA team in manual and Automated testing.

Implementing DAO pattern for database connectivity by using JDBC API.

Developed REST service calls.

Used Oracle database to store data with SQL developer.

Using Maven for build and deployment process.

Developed logging module-using Log4J to create log files to debug as well as trace application.

Environment: Java, J2EE, JSP, Servlets, JDBC, JavaScript, HTML, AJAX, Spring Framework, Eclipse, Oracle

Java Developer at Apple

June 2012 - January 2016 (3 years 7 months)

Apple (GSX)

Responsibilities:

Analyzing new opportunities for my group, this includes daily interaction with business users to get the call data and understand the various problems faced by the field technicians in the field.

Worked as Onsite Coordinator to coordinate the development and project planning activities between Onsite team in Cupertino and Offshore team in India

Was one of the key developers in development of different modules using Java, J2EE, spring, Oracle.

Good hands on experience as a Java developer while working on this project

I was actively involved during requirement gathering phase for this project. During this phase, I was required to understand business requirement from business users, map them to the technology and processes, discuss the functional and technical solution to business users and obtain timely sign off.

Deployment of application to UAT, production environments, resolving issues with other deployment and testing groups.

Involved in every stage of Project including, but not limited to: Requirement Analysis, Detailed Design and Coding

Co-ordination and communication with Client (Apple) team and assignment of work to offshore team Managed to handle multiple threads with ease and speed, Attending multiple meetings around the globe, gathering requirements and implementing the changes

Defect fixing

using JAX-RS and Jersey.

Support IT/UAT phase of multiple projects running in same time and help debugging the complex issues for successful completion of the project cycle.

Very good analytical and debugging skills and fixed very complex application bugs with ease and speed.

Developed SOAP services using JAX-WS annotations.

For some of the modules did a full stack development including Angular JS, JSP, REST, JAVA, J2EE Wrote Client and Server side code to develop REST services and Consume some third part REST service

Senior System Engineer at Infosys

May 2011 - June 2012 (1 year 1 month)

Apple May 2011 to Jun 2012

Senior Systems Engineer

Global Service Exchange (GSX)

Description: Global Service Exchange (GSX) is AppleCare's Repair management tool and entry point for AppleCare service information.

Responsibilities:

- Design and Coding of various JAVA modules
- Design and Coding of User Interfaces using JSP, AJAX and Servlet
- Debug application issues both front end and back end and fix it with ease and speed, Got many appreciations in this area and have confidence to fix any type of technical issues
- I was actively involved during requirement gathering phase for this project. During this phase, I was required to understand business requirement from business users, map them to the technology and processes, discuss the functional and technical solution to business users and obtain timely sign off.
- Deployment of application to UAT, production environments, resolving issues with other deployment and testing groups.
- Involved in every stage of Project including, but not limited to: Requirement Analysis, Detailed Design and Coding
- Co-ordination and communication with Onsite Team. Understand the requirement on phone and implement it.
- Managed to handle multiple threads with ease and speed, Attending multiple meetings around the globe, gathering requirements and implementing the change
- Very good analytical and debugging skills and fixed very complex application bugs with ease and speed

Environment: Java, J2EE, JSP, Servlets, JDBC, JavaScript, HTML, AJAX, Spring Framework, Eclipse, Oracle.

System Engineer at Infosys

September 2008 - April 2011 (2 years 7 months)

Chrysler Sept 2008-Apr 2011

Systems Engineer (Developer)

Activity Tracking Application (ATA)

Description: Activity Tracking Application is a Chrysler internal tool for procurement of Hardware/ Software from various vendors. Automates the Work request, Inventory, Purchase and invoicing workflows, it can be divided into three modules: Work Order system, Inventory Management and Purchasing system. It is targeted at various departments hence making the application generic and customizable.

Responsibilities:

- Involved in the Design, Analysis, Estimation, Coding & Unit testing of Screens
- Responsible for interacting with onsite team, understand the requirement on phone and implement the change.
- Defect fixing after thorough debugging and analysis
- Developing different modules using Java, Struts, DB2.
- Deployment of application to UAT, production environments, resolving issues with other deployment and testing groups.

Education

Dayananda Sagar College Of Engineering

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.), Telecommunications Engineering, 2003 - 2007

Visvesvaraya Technological University

Bachelor's degree, Telecommunications Engineering, 2003 - 2007

Avanish Anand

Senior Java Developer (Contracting at Apple Inc.)



Contact Avanish on LinkedIn